<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | DCS 210</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar.jpg</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a data pipeline for monitoring temperature and biodiversity along the coast of Maine and New Hampshire with NeCSA and Manomet</title>
      <link>/project/necsa-manomet-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/necsa-manomet-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is in collaboration with NeCSA and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.manomet.org&#34;&gt;Manomet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Attitudes Toward Prison Reform and Parole in Maine</title>
      <link>/project/mpac-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/mpac-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Maine was the first state to abolish parole in 1976 and remains one of 16 states that does not offer parole. A reform bill to reinstate parole was recently passed in the house and the senate in Maine (see the full article in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mainepublic.org/courts-and-crime/2021-12-14/a-bill-to-restore-parole-in-maine-passed-in-the-house-and-senate-its-been-sitting-on-janet-mills-desk-for-months&#34;&gt;The Maine Public&lt;/a&gt;. The state legislature announced in April the creation of a 13-member commission to study restoring parole, with a December 1 deadline to make its recommendations (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wmtw.com/article/parole-in-maine/39765482#&#34;&gt;WMTW&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project comes at a critical decision point for Maine. This work will build on work conducted in Professor Amy Douglass&#39; class (Psychology 218) in partnership with the Maine Prisoner Advocacy Coalition (MPAC) which researched perceptions of parole for violent and non-violent crimes and looks at the effect of different justifications on individual&amp;rsquo;s perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an opportunity in this project to look at broad questions including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are Mainer&amp;rsquo;s attitudes towards parole for violent and non-violent crimes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is parole for prisoners portrayed through media and facebook coverage?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What can we learn from other states and country&amp;rsquo;s justice systems about parole outcomes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we use statistics and data to combat misinformation surrounding prison reform including beliefs about how common recidivism is?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project can be developed in several directions, some potential questions include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How has reinstating parole and the reform bill been represented in the Maine media (newspaper, facebook) coverage? Do similar themes emerge when looking at the media coverage and the public&amp;rsquo;s perception of parole?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are parole outcomes in states with parole that are similar to Maine in terms of rural and demographics? Is there evidence for desistance (the reduction in criminal behavior that occurs after a person reaches adulthood)? Is there any statistical basis for individual&amp;rsquo;s perceptions on recidivism (recommitting crimes)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the reform bill is enacted in Maine, how many individuals and who will be eligible for parole?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is in collaboration with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maineprisoneradvocacy.org&#34;&gt;Maine Prisoner Advocacy Coalition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;project-reading-and-resources&#34;&gt;Project Reading and Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nij.ojp.gov/topics/articles/what-does-it-mean-defining-measuring-and-analyzing-desistance-crime-criminal#about-author--0&#34;&gt;Defining, Measuring, and Analyzing Desistance by Prof. Michael Roque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://trends.vera.org/&#34;&gt;Incareration Trends Interactive Map - Vera Institute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vera.org/publications/overlooked-women-and-jails-report&#34;&gt;Overlooked: Women and Jails in an Era of Reform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vera.org/publications/out-of-sight-growth-of-jails-rural-america&#34;&gt;Out of Sight: The Growth of Jails in Rural America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vera.org/publications/divided-justice-black-white-jail-incarceration&#34;&gt;Divided Justice: Trends in Black and White Incarceration 1990-2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vera.org/publications/the-new-dynamics-of-mass-incarceration&#34;&gt;The New Dynamics of Mass Incarceration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mariamekaba.com&#34;&gt;Mariame Kaba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blackandpink.org&#34;&gt;Black and pink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US-wide Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rfordatascience/tidytuesday/tree/master/data/2019/2019-01-22&#34;&gt;The Vera Insitute Data on TidyTuesday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maine Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://csat.bjs.ojp.gov/advanced-query&#34;&gt;The Bureau of Justice Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://justiceresearch.usm.maine.edu/research-library/&#34;&gt;Maine Statistical Analysis Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maine Department of Corrections &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maine.gov/corrections/about/best-practices/reports-statistical-data&#34;&gt;Reports &amp;amp; Statistical Data page&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maine.gov/corrections/sites/maine.gov.corrections/files/inline-files/March%202022%20Monthly%20Adult%20Data%20Report_1.pdf&#34;&gt;monthly report&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.maine.gov/corrections/sites/maine.gov.corrections/files/inline-files/2021%20Year%20End%20Adult%20Data%20Report.pdf&#34;&gt;yearly report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tobacco-use among immigrants in Maine</title>
      <link>/project/akhss-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/akhss-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding tobacco-use among recent immigrants and refugees in Maine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is in partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://akhss.org&#34;&gt;Ak Health and Social Services&lt;/a&gt;, a Lewiston-based nonprofit that connects recent immigrants and refugees with social services such as COVID-19 testing, vaccinations, counseling services, emotional support, need assessments and workforce development.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lyme Disease in Maine</title>
      <link>/project/lyme-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/lyme-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://mmcri.org/?page_id=1090&#34;&gt;Maine Medical Center Research Institute&amp;rsquo;s Lyme and Vector-Borne Disease Lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lyme disease is a debilitating bacterial infection that affects more than X people each year. Spread through ticks, Mass vaccination can greatly reduce the burden of vaccine-preventable diseases such as rabies, however, there is relatively little scientific guidance as to how long control programmes must operate and how they should be best implemented to achieve elimination. My PhD and Postdoc focused on two pivotal questions in infectious disease ecology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the underlying determinants of disease persistence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can vaccination strategies be optimised to eliminate infection?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To answer these questions, I analysed a rich and highly resolved spatial dataset of fox rabies cases and oral rabies vaccination (ORV) programmes throughout Western Europe. The long-term, large-scale nature of these data provides a unique opportunity to improve our understanding of wildlife rabies dynamics in response to vaccination using novel spatial modeling techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
